Papers of Frederick Samuel Dellenbaugh, 1867-1937
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections
Papers of Frederick Samuel Dellenbaugh,
1867-1937
AZ 407
Dellenbaugh, Frederick Samuel,1853-1935
Frederich Samuel Dellenbaugh papers document Dellenbaugh's expedition experiences and studies of the Colorado River and the Southwest
15 ft
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections University of Arizona PO Box 210055 Tucson, AZ 85721-0055 Phone: 520-621-6423 Fax: 520-621-9733 URL: http://speccoll.library.arizona.edu/
Restrictions
There are no restrictions on this collection.
Biographical Note
Frederick Dellenbaugh was born in McConnelsvile, Ohio in 1853. He was an artist, explorer, historian, and writer. Most notably he was a member of John Wesley Powell's Second Colorado River Expedition, 1871-1873, as artist and assistant topographer, and later became historian of the expedition and of the Colorado River. In 1899 he joined the Harriman Alaska Expedition as an artist. Dellenbaugh was one of the founder of the Explorers Club, New York. He wrote a number of books, articles, and short stories about the Powell Expedition, Native Americans, and the West.
Arrangement
This collection is organized into 5 series
Series I: General Correspondence, 1867-1935
Series II: United States Colorado River Expedition, 1869-1934
Series III: Exploreres and Explorations, 1872-1933
Series IV: Writing, 1871-1934
Series V: Art,Architecture, Photography 1871-1934
Series VI: Personal and Family Materials 1889-1937
Scope and Content Note
Correspondence, diaries, notes, manuscripts, clippings, publications, drawings, photo albums, and photographs relating to Dellenbaugh's expedition experiences and studies of the Colorado River and the Southwest. Expedition materials consist of correspondence, photographs of individuals, and articles by Powell and others. Books, articles, short stories, and poems by Dellenbaugh are present, as well as a typescript of 1861 reminiscences by Edward E. Ayer. Also included are photographs of Dellenbaugh's paintings, southwestern Native Americans, and travels; a few taken by E.O. Beaman and John K. Hillers. Correspondents include expedition members, publishers, geographic societies, U.S. government agencies, John Burroughs, Frederick Webb Hodge, William Henry Jackson, Ellsworth and Emery Kolb, Daniel T. MacDougal, Robert Stanton, Robert Taft, John K. Hillers, and William Wallace Bass. Personal materials are diaries (1889-1935), estate papers, W. Norton Goddard family photo albums; and notes, photographs, and maps for a history of Cragsmoor, New York, founded by Dellenbaugh.
Related materials on Frederick Dellenbaugh are available at the Arizona Historical Society.
Dellenbaugh, Frederick Samuel, 1853-1935--Archives.; Powell, John Wesley, 1834-1902.; Burroughs, John, 1837-1921--Correspondence.; Ayer, Edward Everett, 1841-1927.; Hodge, Frederick Webb,1864-1956--Correspondence; Jackson, William Henry,1843-1942--Correspondence.;. Kolb, E. L.(Ellsworth Leonardson), 1876--Correspondence.; MacDougal, Daniel Trembly,1865-1958--Correspondence.; Taft, Robert,1894-1955--Correspondence.; Stanton, Robert Brewster, 1846-1922--Correspondence.; Bass, William Wallace, 1848-1933--Correspondence.; Hillers, John K.,1843-1925.; Beaman, E. O.; Goddard family -- Photographs.; Explorers Club.; Harriman Alaska Expedition,(1899); Explorers -- Southwest, New.; Indians of North America -- Southwest, New -- Photographs.; Colorado River (Colo.-Mexico)--Powell Expeditions; Colorado River (Colo.-Mexico)--Description and travel.; Grand Canyon (Ariz.)--Discovery and exploration.; Cragsmoor (N.Y.)--History.
Container List
- Series I: General Correspondence, 1867-1935
  - A (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Abbot, Stephen: Correspondence, photo, drawing; Enclosure Meagher, J.J. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - American Geographical Society: Bowman, Isaiah (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - American Historical Society (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - American Museum of Natural History/National History: Fisher, G. Clyde (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - American Scenic and Historical Preservation Society: Kunz, George F., Hall, E.H. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Ayer, Edward H.: manuscripts, photo (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - B (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Bandelier, Rann6 R. (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Barret, George: Correspondence related to painting by, with National Gallery of Ireland, Metropolitan Museum of Art, Art Digest, notes, photos (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Bass, William Wallace: correspondence, 2 copies of his Adventures in the Canyons of the Colorado Annotated by FSD (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Berthoud, E.L. (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Bray Pictures Corporation: Bray, J.R., correspondence relative to Colorado River film (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Burroughs, John: Correspondence (John Burroughs; Barrus, Clara; Burroughs, Julian), writings, clippings, photos (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - The John Burroughs Association: Correspondence (Barrus, Clara; Fisher, G. Clyde; Garland, Hamlin; Beebe, William M.), organizational information, program (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - C (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - D (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Dictionary of Architecture, Sturgis, R. (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - E (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - F (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Frazier, Russell E.: Correspondence, photos (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Freeman, Lewis R. (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - G (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Ghent, W.J.: Correspondence;Historians Find Life Story of Forgotten Pioneer; enclosure: Eberstadt, Edward (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Gilbert, G.K.: Correspondence, photo (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - H (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Halladay, Wilford H. (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Heye, George G./Heye Foundation/Museum of the American Indian (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Hodge, Frederick Webb (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - I (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - J (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Jackson, William Henry (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - K (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Kelly, Charles (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Kelly, Dr. Howard A. (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Kolb, Ellsworth L. and Emercy C.: Correspondence, articles, clippings (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - L (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - M (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - MacDougal, D.F. (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - MacMillan Company, Publishers: Correspondence, agreements; see also Dictionary of Architecture (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Meeker, Ezra: Correspondence, clippings (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Middleton, Dr. George W. (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Minnehaha Opera Production: Engels, P.J.; Jarman, R.; Jackson, P.; Rehsen, F.; Grinnell, G.B. (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Moss, Lee J.: Enclosures, Moss, John T. (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - N (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - National Geographic Society: Grosvenor, Gilbert (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - New York City: Police Department; Public Library; University; Zoological Society. See also American Museum of Natural History/Natural History (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - North, Arthur W. and Mary R. (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - O (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - P (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Putnam's G.P., Sons, Publishers: Correspondence (Putnam George H.), contracts, royalty accounts, flyers, notices (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Q (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - R (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Rust, David D.: Correspondence, photos, Boating on the Colorado (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - S (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Smithsonian Institution: Holmes, W.H.; Fewkes, J.W.; Walcott, Charles D.; Graf, J.E. (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Spencer, D.S. (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Stanton, Robert Brewster: Correspondence (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Stanton, Robert Brewster: Correspondence with Jean Oliver Stanton (wife), Anna M. Stanton Burchard (daughter) and Louis F. Burchard (son-in-law) (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Stanton, Robert Brewster: Correspondence with Yale University Press; Clark Arther H. Company, relative to the publication of Stanton manuscript; field notes; dairy extracts; reviews of miscellaneous items (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Stefansson, Vihjalmur: See also Box 6,correspondence and #9, #10, #11 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Stone, Julius F.: Correspondence, photo (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - T (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Taft, Robert: Correspondence, lecture/flyer, Old Photographs. (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - U (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - United States: Correspondence, hearings, reports, etc.: (Box 3, Folder 17)
    Coast and Geodetic Survey
    Commissioner of Indian Affairs
    Defense Department
    Forest Service
    Geographic Board
    Geological Survey: Birdseye, Claude H.; Gregory, Herbert E.; Rizer, H.C.; Smith, George O.
  - United States: (Box 4, Folder 1)
    Interior Department: Finney, E.C.
    Justice Department/Solicitor General: Blackmar, Charles M.; Collins, Randolph S.
    Land Office
    Library of Congress
    National Park Service: Mather, Stephen T.; Tillotson, M.R,; enclosure: McClintock, James H.,February 1, 1933
    Plant Industry
    Post Office Department
    Reclamation: Davis, Arthur Powell; see also Davis, Arthur Powell, BOX 1/17
  - V (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - W (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - White, James: copy of letter to brother H.W. White, 1867; copy of notes on trip; Dawson, Thomas F.: The Grand Canyon (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Whitemore, Frances D. (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Y (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Yale University Press: Correspondence, contracts, royalty statements; Coleman, R.V.; Follett, Soule, L.P. (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Unknown/Unidentified Correspondence (Box 4, Folder 8)
- Series II: United States Colorado River Expedition, 1869-1934
  - Adams, Nathan (Mormon helper):letter (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Bishop, Francis Marion (topographer): Correspondence, obits (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Fennemore, James (photographer)/Fennemore, H.M. (son): Correspondence, photo (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Hamblin, Ben/Helen//Rose H. (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Hawkins, William R. (cook, 1896): Photo (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Hattan, Andrew J. (general assistant): Correspondence, photos, obit (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Hillers, John (Jack) K. (photographer): Correspondence, obit (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Jones, Stephen V. (assistant topographer): Correspondence, diary extracts, clippings (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Powell, John Wesley (expedition leader): Correspondence; copy of agreement with J.C. Summer, W.H. Dunn, O.G. Howland (1869); letter of appointment as expedition head (1874-1874); photo of Emma Dean Powell (wife); correspondence of Mary Dean Powell (daughter), Juliet Powell Rice (sister), and Mary Breasted Powell Paden (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Powell, John Wesley (expedition leader): FSD notes (for Fsd articles about Powell see box 9/5 and 7); clippings, photos, obits (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Powell, John Wesley (expedition leader): Articles by: (Box 5, Folder 11)
    Outlines of the Philosophy of the North American Indians,New York, 1877;Mythologic Philosophy, an address the American. New York, 1877;Mythologic Philosophy, and address before the American Association for the Advancement of Science, Sarasota, New York, 1879
    articles about: Science, November 14. 1902; Minutes of a meeting held...; proceeding the funeral of Major J.W. Powell...; John Wesley Powell, a memorial to an American explore and scholar, edited by Gilbert, Grove, from articles by Bessie Beach, G.K. Gilbert, Grove Karl, Marcus Baker, Paul Carus, Chicago,1903 (a reprint of the G.K.Gilbert article, Chicago 1903 (a reprint of the John Wesley Powell, from the above in "Science", December 27, 1907: Forbes, S.A., History of the Former State Natural History Societies of Illinois; "American Journal of Science", July, 1918: Smith, George O.,A Century of Government Geological Surveys
    Powell,William Bramwell (brother): photo, memorial addresses
  - Powell, John Wesley (expedition leader): Memorials to Grand Canyon, Illinois Wesleyan, Arlington Nation Cemetery: FSD note, sketches, clippings, photos, Lists of personnel, form letter from W.H. Holmes (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Renshaw, Jon H. (general assistant): FSD letters to (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Riley, George (packer, prospector): photos (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Steward, J.F. (assistant geologist: correspondence, correspondence, photo, diary extracts (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Summer, John (Jack) Colton (prospector, 1869): correspondence, photo, obit; FSD note on manuscript; correspondence: Rider, Edgar A. (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Thompson, Almon Harris (2nd in command, geographer): correspondence, photo; Eileen Powell Thompson (wife; sister of JWP): correspondence, photos (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Thompson, Almon Harris (2nd in command, geographer): diary extracts, obits; letters of condolence to widow; financial statement of expedition (1871-1873) with rosters of personnel and annotations by FSD (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Young, Brigham L. (Mormon packer): correspondence (Box 5, Folder 19)
- Series III: Explorers and Explorations, 1906-1933
  - Subseries 1: The Explorers Club, New York City
    - Correspondence, 1906-1924 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence, 1925-1931 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence, 1932 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence, 1933- (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Organizational information, 1933- (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Committees: Locations and moving library (Blossom) inquiry, 1933- (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Special events: annual dinners, lecture series, ladies night, smokers (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Miscellaneous items: flag, Perry medal, bookplate, bell of the cutter Bear, clippings, etc. (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Subseries 2: Explorers and Exploration (Mostly Arctic)
    - Newspaper and magazine clippings; part 1, pp. 1-69 (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - Newspaper and magazine clippings; part 2, pp. 70-136 (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - Other writings by or about explorers, exploration (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - Miscellaneous items: FSD notes, autographed pictures, etc. (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Subseries 3: The Harriman Alaska Expedition
    - Rosters, articles (including FSD, From the Palisades to the diomedesread before the Thursday Evening Club, January 25, 1900, FSD letters to Harriet Otis Dellenbaugh, Taylor (editor, Ellenville Journal), Clara Burus; clippings (Box 6, Folder 13)
- Series IV: Writings, 1872-1933
  - Subseries 1: Manuscripts
    - Hopi Indians (Box 7, Folder 1)
      A Ride to Oraibi
      The Somaikoli Ceremony"
      The Land of the Hopis
      To the Hopi Towns - incomplete
      various fragments and incomplete articles
    - A Long incomplete article, circa 1885 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Other Indians: (Box 7, Folder 3)
      Among the Southern Pai Utes Fifty Years Ago
      Tally Hogan or the Singing House
      The Feast of Soyaita at Sichumovi
      Sunset Fables, how Echo was born
      The Judy Blanket
      The Cave and Cliff Dwellings of the South-West
      The People of the Blue water
      The Aztec Calendar Stone
      The New Metlakahtla Settlement
      The Hermit Tribe of Arizona, incomplete
    - Powell Expedition/Colorado River: (Box 7, Folder 4)
      Data on the killing of three of Major Powell's men...
      Colorado River Exploring Expedition
      "Escalante and the Ute Ford, is Crossing the Fathers a misnomer?(incomplete)
    - Rio Grande Valley: (Box 7, Folder 5)
      The Location of the Rio Grande Pueblos, 1540 to 1630
      The Conquest of the Rio Grande, some relating thereto
      The Location of Cibola and the Historic Towns of the Rio Grande Valley..." (transcription of a talk) various fragments
    - West/autobiographic of western years: (Box 7, Folder 6)
      Buried alive
      Sandstone Paradise
      The Story of a bite
      Concerning the Word 'Estafa'
      The Lost Mine of Espinosa
    - Fiction (Box 7, Folder 7)
      The Pardon of Tenderfoot
      Their Wedding Present
      Patsy's Christmas
      The Figure-head of the Red Dragon
      Daniel's remainder and the Magic Watch(version)
      Professor Lingalem's Language Elixer(3 versions)
    - Fiction (Box 7, Folder 8)
      The Pocketbook
      A Bear Story(incomplete)
      A Crusoe of the Canyon Country(chapter 1, incomplete)
      untitled novel: 2 incomplete chapters; story fragments:
      The Midnight Arrow
      A Piece of Tarred Rope
      others, untitled
      sketch about a Gazeka, written for a competition scenarios/plays: incomplete fragments
    - Poetry (Box 8, Folder 1)
      Gate of the Arctic,(1899)
      My (or The)Trails of Yesteryear; or Lost Trails(3 versions)
      Little Coal Black Coon,1901
      To the Sockdologer, 1933
      The Colorado's Lament, 1933
      The Old Door stone
      untitled
    - Reviews, introductions, letters to the editor (Box 8, Folder 2)
      V. Stefansson's The Friendly Arctic, and R. Farrer's The Rainbow Bridge: reviews
      R.B. Stanton's Colorado River Controversies: review
      Wheeler's Lewis and Clark: Introduction on the United States: letter to the editor
      Another Protest Against Name Change:letter to the editor
      Naming the Grand Canyon:Letter to the edition
    - Canyon and Desert:incomplete chapters from Project recollections of life on the First Mesa in 1884 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Miscellaneous, articles and fragments: (Box 8, Folder 4)
      Phenomenon of Cloud-frost
      Bee-hunting(incomplete)
      Granddad's Château
      Hudson and Fulton
      Peter Skene Ogden, sketch of his life
      article about Florence, Italy
      Log House Building
      incomplete article on building a log cabin
      As It Was Thengroup of very short pieces
  - Subseries 2: Published Newspaper and Magazine Pieces
    - Shorter pieces: comments, reviews, letters to the editor, etc.: Part 1 (1877-1934), pp. 1-25 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Shorter pieces: Part 2 (1877-1933), pp. 26-74, Longer pieces (dates, unless noted, are of publications) (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - Colorado Day,broadside poem (written 1872) with hand colored woodcut after a painting by FSD; 2 copies, initialled, and 2 copies of printed explanation, Concarnewau; An episode in Circle Valley; 1883; (1894) (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - An Artist's Glimpse of Northern Arizona, The First Americans; A Singular Case(American newspaper publication,);; Death Masks in Ancient American Potter;reprint; The True Route of Coronado's march,reprint (1899); 2 copies, one annotated by FSD; 1889; 1893; 1897 (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - The Quick Horse, Fabric-marked Pottery; Architectural Forms in Nature;; John Wesley Powell,a brief review of his career, reprint (the epilogue from The Romance of the Colorado River, New York, 1903; 1898 (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - A New Valley of Wonders, Notes on the Location of Tiguex,with map annotated by FDS (published as an advertising flyer,); The Library of the American Geographic Society;; Cross-cutting and Retrograding of Steam Beds;reprint; Library of Congress: The Lowery Collection;; The Evolution of the Mind in Its Bearing on Woman's Suffragereview;; A Canyon Voyage; 1904; 1905; 1911; 1912 (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - Archdeacon Stucks' Conquest of Mount McKinley, The Somaikli Dance at Sichumovi; Memorial to John Wesley Powell,reprint; 3 signed copies;; Lumholtz, Carl:Through Central Borneo, review;; Alter, Cecil: James Bridger: Trapper, Frontiersman, Scout, and Guide, review;; The Painted Desert;reprints; The Bell of the Cutter Bear, short broadside poem read before the Explorers Club, reprint;; Naming the Grand Canyon;; The Hardenberghs, reprint; 1914; 1915; 1918; 1921; 1926; 1932; May 20, 1933; 1933 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Subseries 3: Books:
    - BREAKING THE WILDERNESS: reviews and notices (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - A CANYON VOYAGE: notebooks and notes, drafts for preface to Yale University Press edition with galleys (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - A CANYON VOYAGE: reviews and notices, both editions (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - A CANYON VOYAGE:(copy 1), G.P. Putnam's Sons, New York, 1908. Autographed with notes and annotations; tipped letter fro Edwin W. Winter, 1927 (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - Letter to Postmaster, Lodore, Colorado, letter from Helen Hamblin; letter from Nathan Adams,; letter from Clyde Eddy,; letters from U.S. Geological Survey,; 1924;; 1922;; 1909;; 1927;; 1906; Enclosures for a CANYON VOYAGE(copy 1): (Box 11, Folder 2)
    - Special boxed edition; given to the Kolb brothers and carried by them on their Canyon trip of 1911-1912, then given back to FSD (see BOX 12/4), 1908.; A CANYON VOYAGE(copy 2), G.P. Putnam's Sons, New York, (Box 11, Folder 3)
    - Notes and annotations, 1926.; A CANYON VOYAGE(copy 3), Yale University Press, New Haven, (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - Letter from G.D.B. Hasbrouck, review; photo, Emery Carl Lehnert; 1934;; 1927;; Enclosures for A CANYON VOYAGE(copy 3): (Box 12, Folder 2)
    - Notes and annotations, 1926; A CANYON VOYAGE(copy 4): Yale University Press, New Haven, (Box 12, Folder 3)
    - Letter from R.M. Broadhurst, bill from Putnam's; 1926; 1922 (probably should be 1911); Enclosures for A CANYON VOYAGE(copy 4): (Box 12, Folder 2)
    - Articles, clippings; pictures,; correspondence, mostly with Elizabeth B. Custer; CUSTER: (Box 13, Folder 1)
    - Notes, manuscripts; fragments,; reviews; CUSTER: (Box 13, Folder 2)
    - notes, drawings; clippings,; outlines,; maps,; ESCALANTE: (Box 13, Folder 3)
    - Notes and notebooks, FREMONT AND '49: (Box 14, Folder 1)
    - Articles, clippings; photos; FREMONT AND '49: (Box 14, Folder 2)
    - notices, reviews; maps; correspondence, mostly with Elizabeth Benton Fremont; FREMONT AND '49: (Box 14, Folder 3)
    - flyers, review; THE NORTH AMERICANS OF YESTERDAY: (Box 14, Folder 4)
    - Notes, map; photos,; flyers;; another copy of contract between Powell and summer/Dunn/Howland; THE ROMANCE OF THE COLORADO RIVER: (Box 14, Folder 5)
    - FREMONT AND "49 (copy 1), G.P. Putnam's Sons, New York, 1914. Signed (Box 15, Folder 1)
    - FREMONT AND "49 (copy 2), G.P. Putnam's Sons, New York, 1914. Signed (Box 16, Folder 1)
    - THE ROMANCE OF THE COLORADO RIVER, G.P. Putnam's Sons, New Your, 1906. Presented to Frederick S. Dellenbaugh 3d, December 25, 1934 (Box 17, Folder 1)
  - Subseries 1: Notes on Other writing Projects:
    - Coronado/Rio Grande Valley: notes (Box 18, Folder 1)
    - Coronado/Rio Grande valley:maps, clippings, drawings (Box 18, Folder 2)
    - Log cabins:articles, pictures, sketches, notes (Box 18, Folder 3)
    - Log cabins:pictures and photographs (Box 18, Folder 4)
    - Meteor Crater, Arizona:notes, jottings, diagrams, writings by others (Box 18, Folder 5)
    - Miscellaneous notes and fragments related to various books and articles (Box 18, Folder 6)
- Series V: Art, Architecture, Photography
  - List of picture (on hand?, sold?), May 1901 (Box 19, Folder 1)
  - Photos of Arizona/West: painting and drawings, 1871- (Box 19, Folder 2)
  - Photos of European paintings and sketches, 1875,1882-1884 (Box 19, Folder 3)
  - Photo of painting of a woman, Ellenville, 188? (Box 19, Folder 4)
  - Photos of Arizona Indians: paintings, 1884-1885, 1890,1933-1934 (Box 19, Folder 5)
  - Photos of Ellenville Knife Works: paintings, 1886-1887 (Box 19, Folder 6)
  - Photos of Ellenville Pottery Works: paintings, 1887 (Box 19, Folder 7)
  - Library, Cragsmoor, New York:Correspondence (with committee and others: Jessica Inness, Grace Curran, Gertrude Wlld, Mary Buxton, Elizabeth Peters, Lawrence Keir, C. and R. Lamb) over planning and construction;various notes, plans, specifications, sketches; dedication by FS, 1925: (Box 20, Folder 1)
  - Chapel of the Holy Names, Cragsmoor, New York: history of FSD,commentary,photos; for the rose window see box 32/1, 1896: (Box 20, Folder 2)
  - Subseries 1: Photograhps
    - Europe, 1906 (Box 20, Folder 3)
    - Canada (Banff, Lake Louise) and Alaska (Box 20, Folder 4)
    - Northern Arizona, Southern Utah (some of these photos may not be by FSD), 1884,1903,1907,1910 (Box 20, Folder 5)
    - Western trip, 1921 (Box 20, Folder 6)
    - Western Trip photos and album, 1929 (Box 20, Folder 7)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 20, Folder 8)
    - Prints of the negatives made by F.S.D. on the First Mesa of the Hopi, 1884 (Box 21, Folder 1)
    - Proof of album of photos made, mostly in Hopiland; pp.1-23, 1884-1885 (Box 21, Folder 2)
    - Proof of album of photos made, mostly in Hopi land pp.24-48, 1884-1885 (Box 21, Folder 3)